So we wanted to find all of the animals that are not gorillas and
لقد أردنا العثور على جميع الحيوانات غير الغوريلاّت
also not named Max.
وغير المُسماة باسم "Max".
So we could do it this way.
يمكننا فعل ذلك بتلك الطريقة.
Select name from animals where not species equals gorilla,
حدِّدوا الاسم من الحيوانات حيث إن (not species = gorilla)،
and not name equals Max.
و (not name = Max)
Or here's another way we can do it.
أو إليكم طريقة أخرى لنفعلها.
There's a logic rule called Demorgans law,
توجد قاعدة منطقية تُسمَّى "قانون دي مورغان"،
that let's us switch not X and not Y into not X or Y.
تُمكِّننا من تحويل "not X وnot Y" إلى "not X أو Y".
So we can say select name from animals where not
لذلك، يمكن أن نقول؛ حدّدوا اسمًا من الحيوانات حيث إن
parenthesis species equals gorilla or name equals max.
not (species =gorilla أو name = max).
That will do the same thing.
سوف ينتج عنها نفس الشيء.
Or hey, here's a third way.
أو، هاي، إليكم طريقة ثالثة.
SQL supports the not equals or bang equals operator, just like python does.
تدعم SQL عامل "not equals" أو ترفض عامل "quals" تمامًا مثلما تفعل python.
So we can say, select name from animals,
لذلك يمكننا أن نقول، حدِّدوا اسمًا من الحيوانات،
where species not equals gorilla, and name not equals Max.
حيث إن (species لا تساوي gorilla) و(name لا يساوي Max).
Any one of those three will work just fine.
ستعمل أيًا من تلك الثلاثة جيدًا.
They'll all produce the same results.
ستقوم بإنتاج نفس النتائج.